In this video, we will be talking about
types
of uncertainties, significant figures, and
how
to calculate with uncertainties. Why do
uncertainties
matter, first of all? Well, uncertainties
matter
because no physical measurement in real
life
is exact. Every single measurement is
limited
by something. For example, instrument
precision,
or experimental technique, or
environmental errors.
So, environment. And because physics
relies
on a lot of measured data, each value has
to
include an uncertainty. And without it,
you
can't really do it effectively.
A measurement is written as x equals x
measured
plus minus the uncertainty.
For example, let's say you want to measure
the
length of a book. You could say the length
would
be equal to 12.4 plus minus 0.1
centimetres.
And this is the uncertainty.
This basically tells the readers, or the
examiner,
that your book has a length between 12.3
and
12.5. There are two types
of uncertainties. There's random
uncertainty
and systematic uncertainty.
Both of these are really stressed in IB.
If you're doing AP, this is probably not
going
to be that important. But if you're doing
IB
and you're going to be doing labs, this is
very,
very important to know. Random uncertainty
is
caused by unpredictable fluctuations.
And it varies from trial to trial.
For example, when you're doing a
stopwatch,
there could be a difference in reaction
time.
However, systematic uncertainty is a
consistent
error, or a consistent bias, in one
direction.
And it can't be reduced by repetition,
while
random can be reduced by repetition.
Can't be reduced by repetition.
An example of this could be a ruler that
has
a missed painting, or the etch marks on
the
ruler are not even. Etch marks on ruler
are
not even. So basically, systematic
uncertainty
skews all your data in one direction,
while
a random uncertainty is basically the more
you
do the experiment, the less random
uncertainty
there will be. How do you estimate
from instruments? How do you actually get
the
instruments? Well, for analog instruments,
which
means things that you can read, for
example,
a ruler. Or, a good thing in chemistry
would
be a graduated cylinder. You could read
the
etch markings. It would be plus-minus-half
smallest division. So what do I mean by
this?
Well, let's say this ruler goes up by one
centimetre,
as most rulers do.
So when you're measuring it, the
uncertainty
of whatever you're measuring with this
ruler
would be plus-minus-0.5 centimetres.
And this would be your uncertainty.
However,
let's say you're measuring with a digital
instrument.
Digital instrument.
And the uncertainty would be plus-minus
the
least significant figure.
Least sig dig.
So basically, in this case, it means that
you
want to plus-minus one of the furthest
decimal
places. So let's say you have a stopwatch,
and
your stopwatch measures, let's say, 2.36.
Well, the least decimal place here would
be
two after the one.
So the uncertainty here would be 0.01
seconds.
And that's basically how to get the
uncertainty
in an experiment. You're going to probably
learn
this in class for IB, but it's good to
know
earlier. Now, how do you calculate with
uncertainties?
Let's say you want to calculate the
velocity
or speed of an object. Velocity is
distance
over time. And let's say your distance is
measured as 5.0 plus-minus one metres.
And your time using your stopwatch could
be,
let's use this, 2.36 seconds plus-minus
0.01
seconds. So when you're multiplying or
dividing
uncertainties, and this is really, really
important
in labs for both physics and chemistry,
you
want to first take the percentage
uncertainty.
If you're not doing IB or high school and
you're
focusing on AP, you don't really need to
worry
about this. This is for lab work. So let's
first
focus on the distance. The percent
uncertainty
for distance would be one, let's say, or
0.1
metres would be a more reasonable
uncertainty.
So 0.1.
So the percent uncertainty here would be
0.1
over 5.0 times 100%.
And when you do that, you would get a
percent
uncertainty of 2.0%.
Same thing for the time, and you get 0.01
over
2.36 times 100%.
And that would be equal to 0.01 divided by
2.36
times 100. The total uncertainty would be
0.4,
0.42.
Sorry, 0.4, yeah, 0.4%.
And how do you get the total uncertainty?
Well, this is what you have to do.
You just add them. Once you have all the
uncertainties
required for division or multiplication,
you
could just add the uncertainties. And the
total
uncertainty would be 2.4%.
So once you calculate what your final
velocity
is, you would get 2.1 metres per second.
You would take this 2.4 uncertainty and
you
would put it into here. So if you do this,
divided
by 100 times 2.1, you get an uncertainty
of
plus minus 0.04 metres per second.
And that would be your final answer.
Make sure that your final digit also
matches
the uncertainty here. So you would have to
add
an extra figure here. But basically that's
how
you calculate uncertainties when you're
dividing
and multiplying. What if you're adding two
values?
Let's say you want to add two distances,
5.0
plus minus 0.1 metres, 0.1 metres.
And then you add that with another
distance
calculation, let's say 6.0 plus minus 0.2
metres.
Well, when you're adding or subtracting,
it's
way easier than when you have to multiply
and
you have to get all the percent
uncertainties
and adding them. You could just add the
directly. Because if you think about it,
these
uncertainties cover the ranges of what you
have
to measure. So by adding them, you are
accounting
for both the ranges. And that's how you
calculate
uncertainty. Remember, for multiplying and
dividing,
you have to convert it to percent
uncertainties,
add it, and then apply it to your final
answer.
However, for adding, you could just
directly
add the uncertainties. I hope this will
give
you a head start on lab work, and I hope
this
helped you. Thank you.